Even if they want to cut down, even if they know
it's killing them, they find they can't stop.
My name is Chris Van Tulleken
and I'm an NHS doctor, I'm a scientist, and I'm part of a growing
group of doctors and academics who are
increasingly worried about the effect that the global food system is having on all of us.
When it comes to obesity, the way that we've understood the problem is it's a failure
of willpower.
People are just making bad choices.
They're somewhat lazy.
It's basically their fault.
This is American
government data for men and women
of all different ages.
The different lines
are different ages for obesity.
What you see is between 1960 and 1975, there's a fairly steady percentage of obesity in the population.
But in the mid 1970s,
obesity starts going up in all of the groups simultaneously.
Now, if you're saying willpower is responsible,
what you're proposing is that all of these groups of people simultaneously lost moral responsibility.
And that's not plausible.
Something else happened to our food in the mid 1970s to make it irresistible to people.
My name is John Ruff, and I've spent 40 years in the food industry across seven different countries.
Companies spend a lot of time
optimising all aspects of their product.
The
flavour, the taste, the texture.
People want their product to be
as good, if not better than the competitor, so it will sell more.
We use trained sensory panels to give
us ratings.
Is it squishy?
Is it hard?
Is it soft?
Is it crunchy?
That's very much how the food
industry operates.
One thing many people don’t realise is
that factory processing changes the textural properties of food.
An interesting fact
about soft food is you're not chewing
it as much.
That actually short circuits the normal satiety mechanisms
that you would have if you were actually chewing food properly.
So, you're bypassing a normal mechanism
that tells you you're full.
Once we worked out that playing around with the
texture of food, making it softer, tricks that normal satiety of fullness mechanism, clearly there's an opportunity
there for some kind of scurrilous behaviour in making food softer, so that people will eat more and therefore you sell
more of your product.
So much of the packaged food
that we eat is incredibly soft.
My kids love these.
You don't typically
think of this as being a soft food because it's a bit crunchy.
But actually after that
initial crunch, you can just crush it
with your tongue, right?
It's got no resistance
at all.
But in terms of the
calories per gram, it's got way more calories than
even a very fatty burger.
So, the softness and the energy density mean that you consume it incredibly quickly.
And there's a food
industry term for these very light, puffy foods that melt in the mouth.
It's called vanishing
caloric density.
Gone.
The thing that makes us eat
a lot isn't just what we do to the food.
It's also about logos, marketing, branding, the box the
food comes in.
Eating is a multi-sensory experience.
There's the look of the food.
There's the smell of the food.
There's the feeling of the food on your fingers.
Even the sound of
food matters.
When you open a fizzy soda, you've got two noises.
You've got the click and the tear.
Sound engineers and manufacturers work really hard to get that sound just right.
And that’s sonic branding.
Many companies have asked me to work on sonic
branding for them.
And I think I can mention
when I was working with Kellogg, they
said, “Ooh, what’s sonic branding?
” And I said, “You
invented this.
” Most people will remember
as children the experience of lifting a bowl to their ear.
And what are they
listening for?
Snap, crackle and pop.
That's sonic branding at its best, and that's the original.
There's a lot of competition
out there, and food companies
make their money by the amount of products
we consume from them.
So, there's a stomach share that they're fighting for and there are hours in the day in between breakfast,
lunch and dinner.
What happens between
those hours?
They want us to snack.
You wake up and this
is what you have.
Snack number one.
Breakfast shake, ultra-processed.
This is heavily marketed for you to
have on the go.
Do not sit down.
Do not take time to crunch through something.
Snack number two of the day.
It's empty calories, energy dense, nutrient poor.
Midday, you're starting to get
a little bit peckish, and what do you have?
Veggie straws.
This is a good example of a health claim snacking product.
Whereas before we would
have had food.
Actual food.
Now we are marketed
into believing that this is actually a
healthy replacement.
Some snacking products
have now been made to be linked with being physically active.
So, after the gym
I have a high protein, low sugar bar.
Instead of having a healthier option.
You finish having dinner and you have these snacks that are sold to you as more to share, where in fact you can
just finish them, watching the TV by yourself.
I do like them.
I cannot stop eating them.
And I literally can't.
Oh God.
I think one of the biggest problems with this kind of food is that so many of us struggle to stop eating it.
Hi everyone.
I'm so thrilled to be here
today to speak with you on my research that looks at parallels between addictive substances
and ultra-processed food.
When we look at the sorts
of foods that trigger those key diagnostic indicators of addiction, it's really clear
what it's not.
It's not minimally processed foods like fruit or vegetables or beans or lean meats like
chicken breast.
It's really processed foods.
It's chocolate.
It's ice cream.
It's pizza.
It's foods that don't
exist in nature.
The potency and the reward power of these ultra-processed foods can trigger an
addictive response that leads them
to consume these in such a compulsive way, that even if they want
to cut down, even if they know
it's killing them, they find they can't stop.
Imagine you're trying to cut down on
ultra-processed food or avoid it altogether.
For a start, it might be the only food
you can afford, and that is true
for millions of people, but it's everywhere.
And it's engineered
and then marketed by some of the smartest people on Earth to be irresistible.
So, if someone is watching this and they are struggling
with their weight, with diet-related disease, I just want to reach out
and grab them and go, “This is not your fault.
It is not you.
It is the food.
” [Narration]
The Food and Drink Federation declined
our request for an interview
but provided this statement.
“Food and drink manufacturers take
the issue of obesity and poor diets very seriously,
and we know we have a key role to play in helping
people to eat balanced diets.
Our members continue to invest hundreds
of millions of pounds in creating healthier products
for shoppers.
As a result, UK shopping baskets now contain significantly less salt, sugar and calories
than they did a decade ago.
Companies are also working
to raise the fibre, fruit and vegetable content of their products.
It's of course up
to government if they want to introduce
new taxes or warning labels.
However, taxes will push up the cost of food
and could disincentivise ongoing investment
in healthier products.
We think there are more
effective ways to encourage positive dietary change.
On labelling, we believe the UK's traffic light system is a more positive way of nudging
consumers towards healthier choices
than warning labels, where global evidence suggests the longer
term impact is limited.
However, we would support
a labelling review, including to test whether
consistent positive labelling on all healthier products would help consumers.
The government's
Scientific Advisory Committee on Nutrition has said there's insufficient scientific evidence on the concept of ‘ultra-processed foods’ for it to be used for
dietary guidance or policy making, and that
further research is needed.
If research comes to light, that processing is a cause
for concern, the food industry will
act quickly to change their ingredients
or processes.
”